<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Jones of Hatton-Garden, his book of cures this book dated April the eighteenth, 1673.</title>
            <author>Jones, of Hatton-Garden.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1673</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 74 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A47035</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing J941AB</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R36855</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">16143847</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 16143847</idno>
            <idno type="VID">104839</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A47035)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 104839)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1595:107)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Jones of Hatton-Garden, his book of cures this book dated April the eighteenth, 1673.</title>
                  <author>Jones, of Hatton-Garden.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>12 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1673]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: pages cropped, with some loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Medicine --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Advertising --  Medecine --  England.</term>
               <term>Quacks and quackery --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:104839:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>JONES <hi>of</hi> Hatton-Garden, <hi>his Book of</hi> CURES.</head>
            <head type="sub">This Book dated <hi>April</hi> the Eighteenth, 1673.</head>
            <p>I Shall not need to ſet down what Cures I can do, for there are thouſands will ſay, they can do all manner of great Cures, but where have they cured any? It is not the ſaying I can or would do great Cures, but he that is known to do ſuch Cures you muſt look after, if you intend to have help, and if you pleaſe to read over this little book, you will find that there is but few Cures to be named, but what I have Cured, the Peoples names and places where they live, which are your neighbours round about you, ſo that you need not go far to know the truth of it, neither need you queſtion, but that I ſhall do the ſame Cures ſo long as it pleaſeth God to continue the bleſſing with me, and when he pleaſe to take it away, I ſhall do no more.</p>
            <p>My name is <hi>Jones,</hi> the Engliſh Phyſician, who through the bleſſing of God, with my own induſtry for the ſpace of twenty three years practice on the worſt of Diſtempers, have found out how to help any Diſtemper (ſo far as Curable,) and give my Books and Judgement to all for nothing.</p>
            <p>I live at a corner-houſe in <hi>Hatton-Garden,</hi> in <hi>Holborn,</hi> three doors from the ſign of the <hi>Golden-ball,</hi> almoſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver againſt <hi>Baldwin's Garden-gate,</hi> at the upper corner near the ſign of the <hi>George.</hi> And whereas I ſaid in my former Book, that if I ſtayed any longer than Midſummer next, I would give you notice a quarter of a year be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that time, This is therefore to let you know, that I have taken a new Leaſe of my houſe for two years lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, but I intend, God willing, to go to my Country-houſe at <hi>Marſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>field,</hi> five miles this ſide <hi>Bith,</hi> on the fourteenth day of <hi>June,</hi> every year, and continue there till the 14 day of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> and then <hi>September, October,</hi> and <hi>November</hi> at my houſe in <hi>Hatton-Garden,</hi> then <hi>December, January</hi> and <hi>February</hi> at <hi>Marſhfield,</hi> then <hi>March, april</hi> and <hi>May</hi> at my houſe in <hi>Hatton-Garden;</hi> where I will deal faithfully with you, as I have done, to the great com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of thouſands in and about <hi>London,</hi> ſince my coming, as you may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d of ſome of their names ſet down in this Book. And in my abſence I will leave of my <hi>Cordial-Pill</hi> and <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> of <hi>Balſoms</hi> in Pots, and ſealed with my own Seal, and in the hands of a truſty friend which I will leave on purpoſe in my houſe in <hi>Hatton-Garden,</hi> and another in my houſe at <hi>Marſhfield,</hi> in <hi>Gloceſter-ſhire</hi> whilſt I am here at <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>NOw I will tell you of ſome of the greateſt Cures that have been done in this Age, the peoples names, and places where they live, if you will diligently read over this little book; and as it is ſaid that by the mouths of two witneſſes the truth of a matter ſhall be confirmed, you have not only two witneſſes to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm the truth of this little book, but many: inſomuch that if you will believe that there is any truth in the world, you may believe this. I never practiſed in <hi>London</hi> before the date hereof, being from the third of <hi>June,</hi> 1669. and in this little time have done Cures as followeth, with thouſands more.</p>
            <p>I have with Gods help given help, and Cure according as it is here ſet down. I helpt the wife of Mr. <hi>Richard Su<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rance</hi> of <hi>Tower-hill</hi> two doors from the ſign of the <hi>Black-dog</hi> a Silk-weaver, of great pain of her Head and Stomach, ſhe being ſo weak not likely to live. Mr. <hi>Philip Luke</hi> of the <hi>Neat-houſes,</hi> of the Stone, and have it to ſhew. Mr. <hi>Ralph Swain</hi> at the <hi>Soho,</hi> almoſt over againſt the Prince of <hi>Orange's-head</hi> a Carpenter, of the Ague and Feaver. The wife of Mr. <hi>Charles Parſons,</hi> at the ſign of the <hi>Black-raven</hi> in <hi>Pear-pool-lane,</hi> of a Feaver, with great pain at her Stomach. <hi>Francis Hollis</hi> in <hi>Wapping,</hi> at the ſign of the <hi>water-houſe,</hi> of great pain in his Ancles, who could not get help in three or four years. Mr. <hi>John Worane</hi> near the ſign of the <hi>Crooked-billet</hi> and <hi>Ship</hi> upon the <hi>Green-back</hi> in <hi>Southwark</hi> of the Sciatica and a Feaver. Mr. <hi>William Aſh</hi> of <hi>Bedual-green,</hi> over againſt the old <hi>Chappel,</hi> of the third day Ague and Feaver. Mr. <hi>John Weſton</hi> of the <hi>Neat-houſes</hi> of the third day Ague and Feaver. Mr. <hi>Nicholas White</hi> of <hi>White-hart-yard</hi> in <hi>Eaſt-Smithfield,</hi> of the Conſumption and Cough, and Shortneſs of breath. Mr. <hi>John Davis</hi> of <hi>Pickled-herring-ſtairs,</hi> at the ſign of the <hi>Five Tobacco-pipes,</hi> of the Ague. Mrs. <hi>Clipſon</hi> at <hi>Saffron-hill,</hi> the next door to the <hi>Roul of Tobacco,</hi> of a Cough, who could not get help by any other. The ſon of Mr. <hi>Thomas Billington</hi> a <hi>Baker</hi> in <hi>Peters-lane,</hi> at <hi>Cow-croſs,</hi> the next door to the ſign of the <hi>Fox,</hi> of the Convulſion-fits ever ſince half a year old. Mrs. <hi>Jane Sidow</hi> at the <hi>Back-ſide</hi> in <hi>Southwark,</hi> over againſt <hi>Hollands leger,</hi> near the ſign of the <hi>Two Cats</hi> of a ſad Cough and diſtempered Stomach. Mrs. <hi>Elizabeth Marland</hi> the next door to the ſign of the <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Key</hi> in <hi>Peters-lane</hi> near <hi>Hicks's-Hall</hi> of Deafneſs. Mrs. <hi>Mary Porter</hi> in <hi>Three-Oake-lane,</hi> joining to <hi>Joneſes-<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ane,</hi> near the ſign of the <hi>Dun-Cow</hi> near <hi>Cow-croſs,</hi> of great pain in h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r Legs, who could not get help in two years. Mrs. <hi>Martha wells</hi> of the ſame place of a ſore Leg. The wife of Mr. <hi>Iohn Mead,</hi> the next door to the ſign of the <hi>Sugar-loaf</hi> and <hi>Two Flying<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>orſes</hi> in <hi>Faſhion-ſtreet</hi> near <hi>Spittle-fields,</hi> of <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:104839:2"/>Feltmaker, of Deafneſs, Mrs. <hi>Elizabeth Fiſh</hi> at <hi>Hodſdon,</hi> the next door to the ſign of the <hi>Three Kings</hi> of great pain and lameneſs in all her Limbs, and the gripes of the Guts. I did much good to Mr. <hi>Edw. Mulasi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> Long-acre</hi> in <hi>Coxes-alley,</hi> for a great pain in his Stomach and Back. Mrs. <hi>Mary Pain</hi> at <hi>Holborn-Conduit,</hi> next door to the <hi>Golden-lyon,</hi> of the Cough. Mr. <hi>Will D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> next door to the Church in <hi>Rood-lane</hi> in <hi>Fanchurch-ſtreet,</hi> of an Ulcer in his Leg, of twelve year, and I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> him well in about two months time with Gods help. <hi>Elizabeth Cleverly,</hi> the next door to the <hi>Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e Neats-Tongues</hi> in <hi>Silver-ſtreet</hi> in <hi>Boomsbary,</hi> of the Plith-ſick and ough, who was ſo bad therewith, that ſhe was likely to loſe her ſpeech. Mr. <hi>Ioon Langly</hi> at the Coffee-houſe near the 3 <hi>Cranes</hi> on great <hi>Tower-hill,</hi> of a double third-day Ague. <hi>Mary Moor</hi> at the <hi>Half-moon-Inn</hi> near the <hi>Kings-Bench</hi> in <hi>Southwark,</hi> of Deafneſs. Mr. <hi>Henry Taylor</hi> near <hi>Shoreditch-Church,</hi> at the ſign of the <hi>Cradle,</hi> of the third day Ague and Feaver. Mr. <hi>Edward Curtis,</hi> of the <hi>Neat-houſes,</hi> of great pain and ſtoppage at his Stomach, he is a Gardiner. Mr. <hi>Iohn Baker</hi> a Ship Carpenter at <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ptſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d,</hi> near the ſign of the <hi>Chequer,</hi> of a Feaver, with great pain at his ſide. I did much good to Mrs. <hi>Elizabeth Baker,</hi> the wife of the aforeſaid <hi>Iohn Baker,</hi> for the windy Gout. Mr. <hi>Samuel Chadwell</hi> in <hi>Tully-ſtreet</hi> near <hi>Horſty-down,</hi> the next door to the ſign of the <hi>Worlds-end,</hi> of the Feaver and griping of the Guts, <hi>Southwark.</hi> Mr. <hi>Iohn Wicks</hi> Junior, of <hi>Fig-tree-court</hi> in <hi>Barbican,</hi> at Mr. <hi>Taylors</hi> houſe at the upper end of the Court, of the Dropſie. I did much good to Mrs. <hi>Terill</hi> of the <hi>Red-Lyon</hi> in <hi>Wapping</hi> (the carved <hi>Lyon</hi> and the <hi>Carver</hi> liveth over againſt it) for the Apoplexy and Palſie, all one ſide; I mended her ſpeech alſo. I cured the Child of Mr. <hi>Grimes</hi> living between <hi>Vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e-ſtreet</hi> and <hi>Mutton-lane,</hi> near <hi>Clarken-well,</hi> a Clock-maker, of the Rickets, and Conſumption, when he was almoſt at deaths door. I ſaved the Leg of Mr. <hi>Iohn Hale</hi> of <hi>Angel-all<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y</hi> in <hi>Biſhops-gate-ſtreet,</hi> from retting off. Mr. <hi>Thomas Anyon</hi> in <hi>Bedford-bury,</hi> over againſt the <hi>Tabacco-roul,</hi> of Looſeneſs, and Vomiting, and a Cough, and Feaver, with great pain. Mr. <hi>William Stone</hi> a Seaman in <hi>Wapping,</hi> near the Gun-Tavern, of the Ague and Feaver. The ſon of Mr. <hi>Iames Bell</hi> in the <hi>Cole-yard</hi> in <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ew<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y-lane,</hi> at the upper end of the yard, at Mr. <hi>Lawlys</hi> houſe, of the Feaver and gripes of the Guts. <hi>William Dawſon</hi> in the Red-bull Play-houſe yard near <hi>Clarkenwell-green,</hi> of the Cough, and great pain in his Back. Mr. <hi>Samuel Jones</hi> living near the <hi>Red Lyon</hi> in <hi>Grays-Inn-lane,</hi> of the third-dayes Ague. Mr. <hi>Abel Barton</hi> at the Brew-houſe at the upper end of St. <hi>Iohn-ſtreet,</hi> of the Gout, being near threeſcore years of age, and lay ſo lame with it, that he was not able to turn in his Bed, this being at the Fall of the Leaf, about two years ſince, and he not expected to leave his Bed till the Spring; however with Gods help I made him perfectly well in a month or ſix weeks time. <hi>Alice Baker</hi> over againſt the <hi>Black-ſwan</hi> in <hi>Turnmill-ſtreet</hi> at Mr. <hi>Corners</hi> houſe a Brick-layer, of looſeneſs of her Teeth, when they were all ready to fall out of her head, and made them faſt again, ſhe being near fourſcore years of age. The child of Mr. <hi>Henry, Standly in Red-roſt-ſtreet</hi> in <hi>Covent-Garden,</hi> at the ſign of the <hi>Sedan,</hi> of the Conſumption, when he was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>moſt at deaths-door. Mr. <hi>Iohn Houſe</hi> of <hi>Bull<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>alley</hi> in <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>tby-ſtreet, Southwark,</hi> of the third day Ague and Feaver. Mr. <hi>Shepheard,</hi> next door to the ſign of the <hi>Golden Ball</hi> in <hi>Hatten-Garden</hi> of the New Feaves, and the Gripes of the Guts; and his tongue was as black as Ink, yet with Gods help I made him as well as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> he was in his life. The wife of Mr. <hi>Ralph Holloway</hi> at the Nags-head in <hi>Grayes-Inn-lane,</hi> of a Feaver, with great weakneſs, when none thought ſhe would have lived. The wife of <hi>Iohn Right</hi> of <hi>Brick-lane</hi> in <hi>Old-ſtreet,</hi> in Key and Swar-yard, Deafneſs. Mr. <hi>Iohn Michel</hi> a School-maſter in <hi>Angel-alley</hi> in <hi>Grays-Inn-lane,</hi> of a ſore and Rheumy Eye, who had made tryal of able men for the ſpace of ſeven or eight years, and could not get any remedy, and with Gods help I made him well in nine or ten weeks. I helpt his wife alſo of great pain in her back, I helpt his child alſo of the Chin-cough. Mr. <hi>Thomas Love</hi> near Shore-ditch Church of the Jaundies, he being above fourſcore years of age when he was cured. Mr. <hi>Richard Young</hi> of <hi>Park-ſtreet,</hi> near St. <hi>Alboas,</hi> of a Wen on the top of his head, who could not get help by any other in twenty years, and I took it out at twice dreſſing, not ſpilling one drop of blood. <hi>Elizabeth Brownſier</hi> of <hi>Swan-alley</hi> in the <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ories,</hi> of the <hi>Convuiſion-fits,</hi> and ſhortneſs of Breath. <hi>Sarah Fox</hi> in <hi>Axe-yard</hi> in <hi>Blackman-ſtreet</hi> in <hi>Southwark,</hi> of the Ague. <hi>Iames George</hi> on the <hi>Bark-ſide</hi> near the <hi>Bear-garaen,</hi> in <hi>Southwark,</hi> of great pain in his Shoulders, Arms, and Hips. Mr. <hi>Graves</hi> at the ſign of the <hi>Blind-Begga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> at <hi>Cow-croſs</hi> of the Winid-gout in all his Joints. Mr. <hi>Edward Squire,</hi> in <hi>Goſwell-ſtreet</hi> at Mr. <hi>Matthew B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es</hi> houſe, a Shoo-maker, over againſt the Pump, between the ſign of the Maiden-head and the Bell, of a Cancered Wen in the ſide of his neck, near as big as a penny loaf, which grew faſt to the Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible or Jaw-bone, and the Veins and Sinews grew through it, and I cured him without hurting the Veins and Sinews Inſomuch that none can hardly ſee where it grew, and if he be not there now, Mr. <hi>Brawn,</hi> the man of the aforeſaid houſe can give you an account of this great Cure. <hi>Henry Clarre</hi> of a Conſumption, when he was ſo much waſted that his fleſh was all withered away, that he had not left to cover his bones but the skin; I did never ſee any man ſo bare of fleſh, neither dead nor alive, and uſing my things he grew ſtrong and luſty, and fleſh grew up and covered his bones, in ſo much that he hath as much fleſh on his bones as any ordinary man; and thus we may ſee how God bleſſeth the means ſometimes, contrary to our expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation therefore 'tis good for every one to uſe lawfull meant to the <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:104839:2"/>her Hip, being ſo had therewith that ſhe could not take any reſt night nor day, and I helpt her of that, and alſo of the Fits of the Mother, Aged above fifty. <hi>Robert Dayily</hi> of <hi>Kingſton</hi> upon <hi>Thames,</hi> ten miles from <hi>London,</hi> of the vomiting of blood. The wife of <hi>Nicholas Biſhop,</hi> at the Sign of the Childes Coat in the <hi>Hay-market</hi> at <hi>Pickadilly,</hi> of great pain, with deafneſs, noiſe, and ſinging in her Head. Mr. <hi>William Medbere</hi> of St. <hi>Martines</hi> in the <hi>Fields,</hi> Coach-maker, the next door to the ſign of the Sugar-loaf at a Glaſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>makers, of the Sciatica Gout in his hip, and at times in all his Joynts, who lay very weak, and could not get help by any of a long time, and I gave him caſe of pain in three hours; and in a fortnights time cured him. <hi>Anne Fiſher</hi> of <hi>Church-yard-Alley</hi> in <hi>Chick-lane,</hi> of deafneſs, and ſinging in the head. <hi>Heſter Wood</hi> of <hi>Church-yard-Alley</hi> in <hi>Chick-lane,</hi> of the ſtone in the Bladder, I took away her pain, and brought the Stone from her, in leſs than twelve hours, when ſhe was in ſuch torment that cannot be expreſt, and of great age. I have the ſtone to ſhow any that pleaſe to ſee it. The Son of Mrs. <hi>Mary Clark,</hi> near the ſign of the Lamb in <hi>Iſlington,</hi> of the Lethargy, with great pain in his Head and Deafneſs. Mr. <hi>Adam Prince,</hi> at the ſign of the Boot in <hi>Kings-ſtreet</hi> in <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> of the Stone and Cravel in the Kidneys and Bladder. <hi>Elizabeth Theſon</hi> of <hi>Newington-Buts</hi> in <hi>Blackman-ſtreet</hi> in <hi>Southwark,</hi> in <hi>Lamb-Alley,</hi> of a Cancer in her Breaſt almoſt as big as a mans-head, and I conſumed it away without cutting, or putting her to any pain, or hindering her bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs. <hi>Robert Mills</hi> of <hi>Kent-ſtreet,</hi> the next door to the Roſe, <hi>Southwark,</hi> of the Ague and Feaver. Mr. <hi>Iohn Arnil</hi> at the top of <hi>Saffron-Hill</hi> of the Ague and Feaver. Mrs. <hi>Tomaſin Eſtcot</hi> of <hi>White-Croſs-ſtreet,</hi> in <hi>Bare and Rag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged-ſtaff-Yard,</hi> of a deafneſs, with noiſe in her head. Mr. <hi>Thomas Ward</hi> of <hi>Biſhops-head Court,</hi> in <hi>Gray's-Inn-lane,</hi> of the griping pain in the Guts, and gave him preſent help; I alſo cured his daughter of a Scald or Leproſie head. Mr. <hi>Gregory Coe,</hi> living on the <hi>Bank-ſide</hi> near the <hi>Bear-Garden</hi> in <hi>Southwark,</hi> of the Palſie, who had not the uſe of his hands to cut his meat, or to help himſelf not any manner of way, for the ſpace of three years, and about two months, being near fourſcore years of age, and I ſoon made him well, with Gods help, and he hath the uſe of his hands as well as any of his age. <hi>Michael Smith,</hi> near the ſign of the <hi>Griſffen</hi> in <hi>Ruſſel-ſtreet</hi> in <hi>Covent-Garden,</hi> of great pains in his limbs, and the Cramp. Mr. <hi>Fawey</hi> at the <hi>Black-Raven</hi> in <hi>Long-Acre,</hi> of the Sciatica in his Hip. Mr. <hi>Thomas Day</hi> of <hi>Old-ſtreet</hi> in <hi>Blue-anchor-alley,</hi> of a Fiſtula. <hi>Margaret Wheatley</hi> in <hi>Swan-alley</hi> in the <hi>Minories,</hi> of the Tooth-ach, and alſo of great pain in her Head and Ear. Mr. <hi>Bull,</hi> near the ſign of the <hi>George</hi> in <hi>Grove-ſtreet</hi> in <hi>Hackney,</hi> of the third day Ague.</p>
            <p>I will give you notice of one or two of theſe wicked fellows which do endeavour to cheat you, I ſay, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent your being poyſoned, for thoſe which miniſter Phyſick without a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> if they Care one by chance, they may kill above a hundred to every one, for it is with them as the Band man hit the Hair: it was twelve or thirteen years before I could bring to paſs to miniſter things with ſafery to do good though I both ſtudied and travelled hard, and practiſed continually upon the worſt of Diſtempers in all bodies; which do make me admire the impudence of theſe wicked fellows, who do not at all value the lives of people, ſo they can but cheat them of their money. As one <hi>Bullin</hi> whom I took in out of the Streets and relieved him a whole Winter, otherwiſe he had ſtarved. As alſo one <hi>Perry</hi> a Pottet which I implayed to give out my Books, and to make clean the Streets before my Houſe, till he bred ſuch difference and diſquiet in my Family, that I was fain to put him away; there are many others that Counterfeit my things, but I do not give you notice of it for fear of any hinderance they can do me, for I bleſs God I have enough to maintain me and my Family: but for fear they ſhould poyſon any of the people before they are found out; for I have given you but a hint of the Cheats, to what they are in number.</p>
            <p>Now I will ſet down ſome of the Cures which I have done in the Country, and firſt one great Cure with witneſſes to it, and here followeth a true Copy of the Certificate. He cured me <hi>John Aſhcot</hi> of <hi>Totneſs</hi> in <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>von-ſhire</hi> of the Stone in the Bladder, I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> about Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eſcore years of age when he cured me, I was ſo bad that I was not able to make one drop of water, and my pain was ſo terrible that no tongue is able to expreſs, and he gave me a powder which in ſix hours time broke the Stone to pieces and brought it from me; and from this time my pain left me, and I could make water very well; and was not troubled any more with the Stone or pain; In witneſs whereunto we have put our hands, <hi>John Aſtcot, John Sampſon, Peter Brag, Prolomcus Sampſon, John Sampſon, Zach. Punchad, Anthony Langworth, John Amat,</hi> 1668. This is a true Copy of the Certificate, and any that pleaſe may ſee the Certificate. <hi>Richard Pope</hi> of <hi>Brickham</hi> two miles off <hi>Dartmouth,</hi> of great pain in his ſtomach, ſides and back. <hi>John Beard</hi> of <hi>Totneſs</hi> in <hi>Devonſhire,</hi> of lameneſs in all his Limbs, and I ſoon made him lay by his Crutches. <hi>John Day of Churiton-Buſhel,</hi> nine miles from <hi>Exeter,</hi> of great pain in his head, which black Catharacts breeding in his Eyes, I helpt him of his pain of his head; and alſo the black Catharacts which were breeding in his Eyes, and made him ſee very well, though he was almoſt blind, and did it without putting him to any pain, or putting any thing into his Eyes. <hi>William Blackaller</hi> of <hi>Totneſs</hi> in <hi>Devonſhire,</hi> of the Apopl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>xy and Palſie <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:104839:3"/>and within a reaſonable time with Gods help, recovered him. <hi>William Randal</hi> of <hi>Stook,</hi> three mile-off <hi>Exeter,</hi> of the Megrim, with a Cough, and great pain at his ſtomach and back. <hi>Judeth Doab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> living near the South gate in <hi>Exeter,</hi> at Mr. <hi>William Butlers,</hi> of the Evil and blindneſs. <hi>William F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iggy</hi> of <hi>Glaſton,</hi> four miles from <hi>Wells,</hi> of great pain in his ſide, being aged, and could not get help by any other. Miſtreſs <hi>Suſanna Butſoe</hi> of <hi>Otery,</hi> five miles off <hi>Honington</hi> in <hi>Devonſhire</hi> of the Convulſion Fits; the Fit uſed to take her every day, or every other day, and hold her twelve hours every Fit, and I took away her Fit in a quarter of an hour, and could not hear that ever ſhe was troubled any more therewith. <hi>Robert Brownſy</hi> of <hi>Honington</hi> in <hi>Devonſhire,</hi> of the Cough with pain and weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in all his Body, and I made him able to go about his work in three or four dayes, with Gods help. <hi>Judeth Brownſie</hi> of the ſame Town, of the Collick and Spleen. <hi>Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>cca Phillips</hi> of the ſame Town, of a ſad pain in her Head and Breaſt, ſhe being near fourſcore years of age, and a very weak woman, and had made trial of many, and ſpent much money to no purpoſe, and I gave her ſpeedy Remedy, with Gods help <hi>Mary Wilſon</hi> of <hi>Backeril</hi> Parith, two miles off <hi>Honington,</hi> of looſeneſs of her Te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th when they were ready to fall out of her head. <hi>Suſanna Woran</hi> of <hi>Stockland,</hi> five miles off <hi>Honington,</hi> of the Ague and Feaver. <hi>William Cook</hi> of <hi>Newton Abbot,</hi> of the Ague. Mr. <hi>Wholly</hi> of <hi>Wells,</hi> of Limeneſs, who was not able to riſe out of his bed. <hi>William Grigg</hi> of <hi>Atherford,</hi> ſix miles from <hi>Tauntoa</hi> in <hi>Devonſhire,</hi> of great pain and weakneſs, which was cauſed of a great Surfeit, and all that had him in hand had given him off for a dead m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n, and I gave him preſent eaſe, and cured him. <hi>John Far<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>'s ſon of <hi>Kiſon,</hi> a mile off <hi>Taunton,</hi> of the g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ing pains in the Guts. <hi>Walter Colies</hi> of <hi>Charlton Adom,</hi> eight miles off <hi>Taunton,</hi> of Deafneſs, with noiſe and ſinging in his head, who could nor get help in many years, being of great age when he was cured. And you ſhall hear of ſome of the great C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>res I have done at <hi>Briſtol.</hi> I cured the wife of <hi>William Thomas</hi> in <hi>Cock-lane,</hi> going out of <hi>Care-ſtreet</hi> to <hi>Nicholas-ſtreet</hi> in <hi>Briſtol,</hi> of a Cancer in her lett breaſt and ſide, when they which had her in hand gave her off for a dead woman, the Diſtemper being ſo bad with hardneſs of red, yellow, and black coulours, which was very ſad to behold, and they every day put in a Tent between her Ri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s quite into her body, about the length and bigneſs of a mans ſinger, ſo that I judge the end of the Tent muſt needs go within an inch of her heart; ſhe had alſo a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l Feaver attending o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> her, ſo that there could not any thing be expected but death, I preſently cauſed the Tent to be laid by, and I never applied Tont nor Inſtrument, but gave her preſent eaſe, and cured her in about nine or ten weeks time, with Gods help. <hi>Benjamin Holut,</hi> living in <hi>Swar-lane</hi> Court on the Key in <hi>Briſtal,</hi> of the Third-dayes Ague, who could not get help in twelve or thirteen moneths Mr. <hi>John Brooks</hi> his wife in the back lane without the Caſtie Gate in <hi>Briſtol,</hi> of the Second dayes Ague and Feaver. <hi>Thomas Roads</hi> of <hi>Broud-Mead</hi> of the Phthiſick and Cough, with Conſumption, with an extraordinary great pain and ſtoppage at his ſtomach. <hi>William Patchia</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ear the ſign of the Leg in <hi>Temple-ſtreet</hi> of the Sciatita Gout in his hip, who was ſo lame therewith, that he was fain to creep about the houſe on his hands and knees, being near threeſcore years of age, and could not get help by any other, and I made him as well as ever he was in his life, with Gods help. <hi>Thomas Elot</hi> near the Leg in <hi>Temple-ſtreet</hi> of the Cough. <hi>John Doubting</hi> of <hi>Luence-Mead</hi> of great weakneſs. <hi>Anne Doubting</hi> of the ſame place, being in great danger of death with Feaver and Surfeit, and with Gods help I made her perfect well. <hi>William Day</hi> near the Grey-hound in <hi>Brond-Mead</hi> of Deafreſs, being near threeſcore years of age when he was cured, and I made him as well as ever he was in his life. <hi>James Bramble</hi> of <hi>Downing</hi> in <hi>Maurge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>field</hi> Pariſh, three miles from <hi>Briſtol,</hi> of the Dro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſie, with great pain and ſwelling over all his body, and I took away all pain and ſweeling, and made him as well as ever he was in his life. Mr. <hi>Kympton's</hi> ſon of <hi>Rackly-ſtreet</hi> of the ſhaking Palſie in his head, ſhoulders, arms, hands, and feet; and I made him well in a ſhort time. I did much good to <hi>Deb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rab Wilips</hi> over againſt the Three Kings in the ſame ſtreet for the Fits of the Mother, great pains in her ſtomach, and great weakneſs, who could not get help by any other. Miſtreſs <hi>Colli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s</hi> living near the Caſtle Gate of an Impoſthume in her Ear. Theſe are ſome of the Cures I did at <hi>Briſtol</hi> Now you ſhall hear of ſome of the Cures I have done at <hi>Bath</hi> and <hi>Worminſter</hi> in <hi>Wiltsſhire</hi> and thereabouts. I cured <hi>John Stephens</hi> of <hi>Swanſmick</hi> two mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s off <hi>Bath,</hi> of the Sciatica pain in his hip and ſide, being above threeſcore years of age. <hi>John Cox</hi> of <hi>Bath,</hi> of Lameneſs, who could not get help by any other. <hi>Benjamin</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ot of <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th,</hi> of two ſad Ulcers in his foot. <hi>John Powel</hi> of <hi>Donker<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> three miles off <hi>Bath,</hi> of a Wen in his Eye-brow, he being about thirty years of age, and brought the Wen into the world with him, and he cured him without cutting. <hi>Stephen Higgies</hi> his Child of <hi>Steekly near <hi>Calice</hi> in <hi>Wiltſhire,</hi> of the Rickets and Feaver. <hi>John Sal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>on</hi> of <hi>Marſhfield</hi> in <hi>Gloceſte-ſhire,</hi> of great pain and lameneſs in his ſhouldler. <hi>John Cryars</hi> ſon, about <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:104839:3"/>Ague and vomiting Blood. <hi>Elizabeth Gariſh</hi> of <hi>Worminſter</hi> in <hi>Wiltſhire</hi> of the Conſumption, with great pain at her ſtomach, head, and ſide, who could not get help by any other in three years. <hi>John Butcher</hi> of <hi>Hay-Grove,</hi> a little way out of <hi>Horminſter</hi> of the Cancer in his ſhoulder, neck, and throat, when he was ſo bad, that none would meddle with him but my ſelf, and when I had undertaken him, the Doctors thereabouts laught; and one ſaid he would give me fifty pounds if I cured him, and others likewiſe; but when I had cured him, there was not any would give me a penny but himſelf; however with Gods help, I made him as well as ever he was in his life. <hi>William Davies</hi> his daughter of the ſame town, of the Evil in her neck. <hi>Elizabeth Bacher</hi> of the ſame town, of a Scald, or leprous head, who was twelve or thirteen years of age, and brought it into the world with her; I alſo cured her ſiſter of the ſame Diſtemper. <hi>John Statuban</hi> of <hi>Chicklit,</hi> ſix miles off <hi>Worminſter,</hi> of the Ague. <hi>Anne Penny</hi> of <hi>Froom,</hi> five miles off <hi>Worminſter,</hi> of the Evil in her neck. <hi>Henry Bealing</hi> of <hi>Gilling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> Pariſh, ſeven miles off <hi>Worminſter,</hi> of the Sciarich Gout in his hip and ſide, being about three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcore years of age when he was cured. Theſe are ſome of the Cures which I have done at <hi>Bath</hi> and <hi>Worminſter</hi> in <hi>Wiltſhire,</hi> and now you ſhall hear of ſome of the Cures I have done at <hi>Coventry,</hi> I cured Mr. <hi>Brooks</hi> his daughter of <hi>Fillingſly</hi> three miles off <hi>Coventry,</hi> of the Evil and Blindneſs The wiſe of <hi>Robert Harriſon</hi> of <hi>Cowndon,</hi> a mile off <hi>Counter,</hi> of the Conſumption,</hi> Feaver, Surfeit, Jaundies yellow and black, having theſe five Diſtempers all on her at once, and all that had her in hand had given her off for a dead woman, and yet God was pleaſed to give a bleſſing to the means I uſed for her, and reſtored her to her former health again. <hi>William Hayght</hi> of <hi>Alſly</hi> pariſh, a mile off <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventry,</hi> of the Sciatica pain in his hip. <hi>Samuel Graviner's</hi> ſon of <hi>Coventry,</hi> both the bones of his Arm were broken and ſticked out through the skin, and I made him as well as ever he was in his life. <hi>Elizabeth Weltons</hi> ſon of <hi>Hill-Worton,</hi> ſix miles off <hi>Coventry,</hi> of the Evil and Blindneſs. The wife of <hi>Thomas Wenton</hi> of <hi>Forſhill,</hi> two miles off <hi>Coventry,</hi> of the Mother and Spleen <hi>George Moris</hi> of <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſty,</hi> four miles off <hi>Coventry,</hi> of the Cancer on his Face, who could not get help in fourteen years, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing near threeſcore years of age when he was cured. Theſe are ſome of the Cures I have done at <hi>Coventry,</hi> and now you ſhall hear of ſome of the Cures which I have done in <hi>Northamptonſhire, Darb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſhire, Notting-ham-ſhire,</hi> and thereabouts. I cured <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r. <hi>Hen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y Chap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> of <hi>Monſton,</hi> three miles from <hi>Northampton,</hi> whoſe hand was to be cut off, and I cured him without the loſs of a Joynt. Mr. <hi>F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cis <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>owmans</hi> daughter of <hi>Wott<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> two miles off <hi>Northampton,</hi> of the Palſie, withered Ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d and Arm. Mr. <hi>Vicars</hi> daughter of <hi>Little Oakley,</hi> in <hi>Northampton-ſhire,</hi> of the Evil and Blindneſs. <hi>John Smiths</hi> daughter of <hi>Northampton,</hi> of Convolſion Fits. The wife of <hi>William Lacke</hi> of <hi>Grundon,</hi> ſix miles from <hi>Northampton,</hi> of a Cancer in her neck. The wife of Mr. <hi>Bornham</hi> of <hi>Weſt-hadingham,</hi> ſeven miles off <hi>Northampton,</hi> of lameneſs in her b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ck and hips, which came with Child-bearing, and I ſoon made her throw by her Cru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>es. <hi>Richard King's</hi> child of <hi>Backnell</hi> n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ar <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>worth</hi> in <hi>Northampton-ſhire,</hi> of the Rickets and Feaver, being four years of age, and never could bear a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y ſtrength to ſtand, and I made the Child able to go about the ſtrets in a fortnights tune, with Gods he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>William Rabet</hi> of <hi>Kettering</hi> in <hi>Northamptonſhire,</hi> of the Ague. <hi>Thomas G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> of <hi>Rodington,</hi> three miles off <hi>Northampton,</hi> of the third-day Ague. The wife of <hi>Robert Auſtin</hi> of <hi>Hitchin</hi> in <hi>Hartfor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſhire,</hi> of a lame Leg and ſhrunk Sinews, who could not ſet her foot to the ground, nor get help in twenty years, and I made her as well as ever ſhe was in her life. <hi>Iohn Smith</hi> of <hi>Kings Waldon</hi> three miles off <hi>Hitchin,</hi> of a Wen on his fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head, without any ſcar. <hi>Timothy Robleſon</hi> of <hi>Soothill</hi> pariſh near <hi>Hitchin,</hi> of the third-dayes Ague. <hi>Richard Dear</hi> of <hi>Shillington</hi> three miles off <hi>Hitchin,</hi> of Deafneſs. <hi>Peter Shadbott</hi> of <hi>Gravenſt,</hi> four miles off <hi>Hitchin,</hi> of the Ague. <hi>Matthew Negus</hi> of St. <hi>Needs</hi> of the third-dayes Ague, who could not get help in three years. <hi>John Rock</hi> of <hi>Swacy,</hi> three miles off St. <hi>Ives,</hi> of the Ague <hi>Rober T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ureon</hi> of <hi>Hadinham</hi> in the Iſle of <hi>Ely,</hi> who had kep his bed a long time of Lameneſs with great pains, and could not get help by any, and I cured him in one weeks time, with Gods help Mr. <hi>John Acton</hi> of <hi>Howbick Hall</hi> near <hi>Work<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>p</hi> in <hi>Nottinghamſhire,</hi> who had been quite deaf above twenty years, being about fourſcore years of age, and I made him hear as well as any, in a month or ſix weeks time. <hi>Robert Pillngs</hi> of <hi>Nottingham,</hi> of the Ague <hi>Thomas Rainer</hi> of the ſame town, of ſix Ulcers in his Leg, who could not get help in many years. The wife of <hi>William Biges</hi> a Smith in <hi>Darby,</hi> of the Mother and Spleen. <hi>Thomas Foſter</hi> of <hi>Darby,</hi> of the Scurvy all over his body. <hi>Mary Tomlins</hi> of <hi>Ilkuſton</hi> on the Hill near <hi>Darby,</hi> of the Evil in her hand. <hi>Margaret Vaſlance</hi> of <hi>Long-Moſton</hi> near <hi>Woſworth</hi> in <hi>Darbyſhire,</hi> of the Evil in her Neck. Mr. <hi>Cook</hi> of <hi>Spal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ock,</hi> three miles off St. <hi>Needs,</hi> of the Sciatica Goat. <hi>John Lodſon</hi> of <hi>Southward</hi> near St. <hi>Needs,</hi> of the Evil and Blindneſs.</p>
            <p>Theſe witneſſes I ſuppoſe are ſufficient (although I could produce many more) to aſcertain the truth, but to thoſe that will not be perſwaded from the mouths of ſo many witneſſes, it is altogether in vain to uſe any further Arguments. I know there are many perſons which make it their buſineſs to caſt an Odium upon <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:104839:4"/>
            <p>THis my <hi>Balſom</hi> helps the Tetter, Ring-worm, Shingles, or any ſorts of Worms in the Face, Noſe. Mouth, Teeth, and Gums. It helpeth the Tooth-ach, and faſteneth looſe Teeth, though they are read<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to fall out; It will ſoon take away the Scurvies out of the Gums, and help any ſoreneſs in the Mouth and Throat. It will help any ſort of Head-ach, and is preſent help for bleeding at the noſe if you put it up plentifully into that noſtril that bleedeth, and hold it cloſe on to the ſide of the griſſel of the Noſe where the vein is broken, and it helpeth preſently. For the Head-ach, anoint the Noſtrils, and Temples, but if you have not preſent eaſe by ſo doing, anoint the Head where the pain is, and in ſo doing I never knew it fail: for the Tooth-ach, apply it to that Tooth and Gum that acheth, with a little fine linnen ragg, and wear it as a plaiſter, and ſo faſt as the rheume waſheth it away, put on another till the pain is gone, which is moſt commonly in leſs than a quarter of an hour: for looſe Teeth apply it as for the Tooth-ach, and wear the plaiſter all night, and it will not fail you: and for ſoreneſs in the Mouth, and foul Teeth, you may anoint the Mouth, and for a ſore Throat, take as much as a ſmall Nut every night going to bed. It doth help the Conſumption and Cough, by taking the quantity of a ſmall Nut in the morning faſting, and laſt at night. It will help the Running of the Reins, Gonorrhea, weakneſs and waſting in the Back, and the heat and waſting of the Kidneys and Reins by taking the quantity of a ſmall Nut evening and morning; this kind of waſt is very dangerous, and you may know it by a thin white cloud on the top of your Urine in the morning, or a bricky ſubſtance ſticking to the bottom and ſides of the pot. It will take away the Leproſie at two or three dreſſings though they bring it into the world with them, that is outwardly, but they muſt take ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to take away the cauſe inwardly; for the Cramp, you muſt rub it well into the part grieved with your full hand, and it taketh it away preſently; and if you will help the ſhrinking ſinews, you muſt wear it on the part grieved with a piece of thin bladder, to keep it ſoaking in, and ſometimes bath it well in with the heat of the fire. It doth not fail curing a Stinking Breath that proceedeth from the Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach, and when you would not have any to ſmell your Breath, rub a little of it up in your Noſtrils. All Itch and Scabs by anointing. All ſorts of Worms in the Stomach and belly of old and young, by ancint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Stomach and Belly for three or four nights going to bed, it doth aſſwage the Bellies of Children which are ſwelled, and ſometimes gently purgeth, if the Body be foul: but you muſt bath it well in with the heat of the fire, morning and evening, and lay a linnen cloth warm thereon; and ſo wear it for pains in the Stomach, ſides, and belly, you muſt chafe it well in with the heat of the fire, and then apply it with a piece of thin Bladder and ſo wear it; for the pain of the B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ck in like manner, only do not rub it in, but wear it as a plaiſter only: for the Piles and Hemorthoids anoint the part grieved. It helpeth pains in the Feet, ſore Nails, or any dead fleſh that groweth thereon by applying it with a piece of thin bladder to keep it ſoaking in. It will Cure a new wound with a few dreſſings, though the Member be cut three parts off, if you take it quickly and bind it up plentifully with the <hi>Balſom,</hi> and renew it once in a day, and in a few dayes it will grow together again: it will help if a man be run through a Leg or Arm, if it be taken at the firſt and applied plentifully round the member grieved, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>enew it morning and evening: and for any ſort of old ſores, you muſt apply it as a plaiſter morning and evening, and it will cure though the bones be half rotted off, but you need not apply any tent with it not to any new or old ſores; take it upon my word, I do believe it is the beſt that ever was found out for old and new ſores both in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and outward. It giveth comfortable reſt by anointing the Noſtrils and Temples going to bed, that is if the body be not very foul; it will diſſolve and cure hard kernels, and knobs that grow in the necks of boyes and girles without pain or breaking the skin. It taketh away red pimples, or any ſuch like Diſtemper in the face, killeth the black-headed worms in the face and noſe, by anointing when you go to bed; it giveth preſent help for any ſharp humour that breaketh out, but you muſt anoint for that out once in two or three dayes. It helpt Mr. <hi>Bailiff</hi> a Scrivener in <hi>Chippingham</hi> in <hi>Wilts-ſhire</hi> of the ſhaking Palſie, by applying it to the wriſts for three or four dayes, in ſo much that ſome Gentlemen of the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey thereabouts, would not believe till they had ſeen, but ſent for him and me alſo; and when they ſaw he could lift a glaſs of beer to his mouth without ſpilling, they believed becauſe they knew he had not any ſuch uſe of his hands of a long time before. However it hath done greater Cures ſince, for inſtance one Mr. <hi>Gregory Coe</hi> living on the <hi>Bank-ſide</hi> near the <hi>Bear-garden,</hi> of the Palſie, who had not the uſe of his hands to cut his meat for ſome years, being near fourſcore years of age, and by the means of this my <hi>Balſom</hi> of <hi>Balſoms</hi> he ſoon had good uſe of them. It did help Mr. <hi>Ward</hi> of <hi>Grunden</hi> ſix miles from <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thampton</hi> of the Palſie, when he was not able to turn in his bed, and no other means would do him any good. I could mention many which have been Cured by applying my <hi>Balſom</hi> to the Member grieved, and it faileth not doing good for the Palſie; it will ſoon take away all pains from the ſhoulders, armes, hands, knees, ankles, and feet, by applying it with a piece of thin bladder as aforeſaid. It helpeth any kind of ſore Breaſts: It did ſave and help the wife of Mr. <hi>Richard Yockney</hi> of <hi>Wall. Minſter</hi> in <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>
               <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:104839:4"/>well. It doth Cure any fleſhy Rupture by applying it to the part grieved: it giveth caſe to children breeding Teeth by anointing the part grieved on the out-ſide. It helpeth thoſe whoſe limbs are waſting, and their fleſh withering away if they be not too far ſpent. It will give preſent eaſe for the Fiſtula in the Hip, or any other part of the Body, when no other means will do any good, and will bring out the little pieces of rotted bones without pain. It Cureth and giveth preſent eaſe for all Burnings and Scaldings, and taketh away the pain ſo ſoon as laid to the part grieved. I have taken notice, that when I have ſcalded or burnt my ſinger, I have applied my <hi>Balſom,</hi> and it hath given eaſe of the pain ſo ſoon as I have laid it on, and taken out the fire in two or three hours, ſo it does in any kind of burning and ſcalding if it be not bliſtered before you lay it on; which if it be, it will require a little longer time. And for Surfits, want of Appetite, want of quiet Sleep, or any ſudden Diſtemper, you may take as much as a ſmall Nut going to bed, and you will find good for moſt Diſtempers, if it be taken when any Diſtemper firſt takes you. It will cure all Squats and Bruiſes, Strains in the back, or any part of the body, or thoſe that get Scrains with over-lifting; I do believe, that if it were poſſible for a man to live and practiſe with it one hundred years, that one might make it cure all diſeaſes both inward and outward. I fell it in pots one ounce for a ſhilling, and they that have a pound together have it cheaper; It will laſt good forty years, it is good Merchandize in other Countreys, and I believe thoſe that take this and my <hi>Cordial Pill</hi> with them upon that account, muſt needs get twenty for one.</p>
            <p>I never heard that the Cheats did ever give any Books before I came to <hi>London,</hi> and gave out my Books, but now many of them make Books like my former Book, and there tell you a fine ſtory of a Cock and a Bull, how they have things to cure all diſeaſes, but cannot tell you of any cures that ever they did; I do believe there is a thouſand Cheats to every one that deals honeſtly, that will pretend to do cures, and you cannot know them one from the other but by their works, he that cheats you will pleaſe you better in words than he that deals honeſtly, but where are the Cures they have done all this while, have they practiſed ſo long and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver did one Cure, ſurely they are unfortunate Phyſitians that are not able to ſpeake of one Cure they have done, it may be they will tell you a lye and ſhow you a reaſon for it, ſay they will not ſpeak of the Cures they have done for ſome good reaſon, but ſay they we could put the names of hundreds in our Books but will not; but if you will know the right truth why they do not put the names of ſome in their Books, becauſe they never cured any body, and that is the true reaſon why they put none into their Books. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let them not try experience on your bodys, but find out ſuch as are known to do great Cures, make uſe of them; and let not theſe young Doctors practiſe on your bodys, for fear you loſe your money and your lives alſo. Pray inquire of the Cures I have done, they that are honeſt will ſpeak the truth.</p>
            <p>NOw I will ſet down ſome of the virtues of my <hi>Cordial-Pill:</hi> it helpeth any ſort of ſore and Rheumie Eyes though never ſo bad, all ſwelling in the Face, Lips, and Noſe, it helpeth Melancholy and cheareth the Spirits. It will help thoſe which are Mad, or through abundance of Melancholy are grown fooliſh, it expelleth wind upward and downward, ſtrengtheneth the Stomach, cleanſeth the Head, Stomach, Kidneys, Reins and Bladder of all tough ſlimie Humors which nature is not able to carry away; and all ſharp humors which breed Cancers or Kankers in the mouth, and at the root of the Tongue, which you may ſee when they are breeding if you draw forth the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ongue a little way ſide-wayes, then you may ſee the tongue will be a little raw on both ſides near the throat, then is the Blood throughout the whole Body corrupted: this Diſtemper moſt commonly breedeth without pain, and that is the reaſon ſo many die of it, becauſe they ſeek not for help till it is too late, but when it doth begin to be painfull, they are almoſt paſt Cure, becauſe the blood is all Aduſt. This diſtemper is very dangerous and caufeth many a terrible death, it is cauſed by a ſharp humour that diſtilleth down from the brain, and this <hi>Cordial Pill</hi> drieth and carrieth away all ſuch ſharp and mixed humors which breed this Diſtemper, which to the beſt of my knowledge there is not any thing in the world like it, for taking away ſuch humors; it is continually drawing of all tough ſlimie humors from all parts of the body, which no other medicine will or can reach, and it doth it by its gentle and mild ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration; for if you eat as much as a ſmall Nut of it in the morning faſting before you go about your buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs you ſhall ſeldom hear any more of it till ſix or eight hours after, and then it may give you two or three ſtools; and not gripe nor diſtemper you in all this time: and if you take a like quantity when you go to bed, it will do the like in the morning; and note that whatſoever humour offendeth it bringeth it off, as in ſome it bringeth away green Choler, in a other black Choler, and in another yellow Choler, and in another thin watry humours mixed with yellow and black, and ſometimes mixed with green according as they are gendred in the body, and it is ſuch a friend to Nature, that they joyn hand in hand to drive <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> it is received into the body <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:104839:5"/>it doth correct the ſharpneſs of all tough ſlimy humours, and draweth them back out of the Veins and Arteries to the Stomach, and ſo ſends them away down through the bowels, and ſo by that means it leav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not any foul corner of the body unſwept, and reaſon will tell you that if three or four ounces of it wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> cure ſuch a diſtemper of Melancholy as you read before, that there can but few diſtempers come amiſs but what it doth good for, and them I ſhall name at the latter end; and you know it is but two ſhillings the ounce, and that ſerveth ten or twelve times taking and hinders no buſineſs, and reaſon will alſo tell you, that if it will carry off ſuch tough ſharp mixed humours, it muſt needs take away the Scurvey out of the body both Root &amp; Branch, and the Dropſie and all other diſtempers that joyneth with it, and reaſon may tell you alſo, that if it draweth away all this vicious matter out of the Veins and Arteries, that it muſt needs free the Liver and Spleen of all obſtructions, and ſo by that means helpeth the Fits of the Mother and Spleen, and all other diſtempers which are cauſed by that obſtruction: and you may underſtand that by the drawing away this vicious matter out of the Veins and Arteries it muſt needs cleanſe the whole maſs of blood to the purpoſe, and by that means help the Gonorrhea, running of the Reins, and waſting weakeneſs in the Back, Kidneys, and dryeth up all Venereal diſtempers, and reſtoreth to ſtrength; it doth ſo much cleanſe the blood of all melancholy, that in young people it changes the colour of the black and ſwarthy skin, it is good for them that are well to take it Spring and Fall to preſerve health, for it will not ſuffer any foul and novſom humours to breed in the body. It is good for nurſes which give ſuck, for it will cleanſe her Blood, and cauſes good and wholſome Milk, for the Milk is bred of her Blood, and ſometimes her Blood being hot and foul, cauſeth the child to be ſickly and cannot go to ſtool but ſeldom; this being taken a little now and then as aforeſaid will keep her Milk in good order, and the Childs body alſo; and in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard it doth draw away all rough ſlimy humours out of the Veines and Arteries, reaſon will tell you that it is ſuch humours which breedeth the Stone, Sand and Gravel in the Kidneys, Reins and Bladder, and therefore by taking away thoſe humours muſt needs prevent the breeding of the Stone, and alſo the Sand and Gravil; It will not help the Conſumption, nor no ſort of Feaver, nor the Jaundice, nor the Gripes, nor looſeneſs; but for any other diſtemper there is hardly any but it doth good for it. A Man or a Woman may eaſie to work may take of it once a day as much as a ſmall Nut in the morning before you go forth about your buſineſs; and it will give you two or three ſtools in the afternoon, and if you take the ſame quantity going to bed it will do the like in the morning; and for Children give them a little bit according to their age and ſtrength, and diſſolve it in any liquid thing the Child will take it in; it hath a plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant taſte, and you may eat it as you eat bread, or roll it in little balls, or diſſolve it in any thing any way, ſo it goeth into the body, it will do its work; you cannot err in giving it to Children, for it is as ſafe as a bit of bread. I ſell it for two ſhillings the ounce, and one ounce will ſerve ten or twelve times taking for a Man or Woman, and for a Child or young People it will ſerve many times. This my <hi>Cordial Pill</hi> and my <hi>Balſom</hi> of <hi>Balſoms</hi> laſteth good forty years. And note, that violent purges cannot carry off ſuch ſharp and mixed hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors, becauſe they go ſpeedily through the body and leave the diſtemper behind, and make the body weak to little purpoſe. Now this my <hi>Cordial Pill</hi> is always gently drawing it away night and day, and weakens not the body, nor hinders labour.</p>
            <p>I have another ſort of <hi>Balſom</hi> which is taken inward only for ulcerated Gonorrhea, it giveth eaſe for that, and for Ulcers in the Bladder and Kidneys, and preſently taketh away the ſharpneſs of Urine, and helps diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty in making water. It doth cauſe a freſh lively colour in the Face, and cheareth the Spirits exceedingly, it muſt be taken as much as a ſmall Nut every morning faſting; I ſell it for Five ſhillings the Ounce, and that will ſerve ten or twelve times taking.</p>
            <p>I make a Water that infallibly cureth the Sciatica pain in the Hip, if the Bone be not out, the price is five ſhillings the two quarts, and moſt commonly that quantity doth the work.</p>
            <p>I have a Powder that doth often break the Stone in the Bladder, and bringeth it away in Sand and Gravil; the price is half a Crown the Ounce, a Man or a Woman may take as much as will lie upon a ſhilling in a draught or <hi>White-Wine</hi> every morning and evening, and for Children as much as will lie on a two pence a groat, ſix pence: you cannot err in giving it, it is ſo ſafe.</p>
            <p>This thing though ſmall in quantity yet it doth good, according as it is here ſet down, as I have found by mine own Experience. It giveth preſent eaſe and comfort to a diſquiet mind and wandering diſpairing thoughts, which is as bad a Diſtemper as any is. It ſtrengtheneth the Memory exceedingly, and ſometimes recovereth the Senſes loſt. It drieth up all manner of Rheume which diſtilleth down from the Head, which doth many times breed Ulcers in the Mouth, in the Lungs, and Cancers in the Throat, and alſo a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption and Cough. It taketh away this Rheume though never ſo ſharp, it abateth it within an hours time, it ſtrengthens the Stomach, purgeth Wind downwards Twenty four hours every time you take it. That is, if <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:104839:5"/>to the Head, which make ſome Women by Fits as if they had loſt part of their Senſes. It doth help Swimming in the Head and Swouning fits. It helpeth the Dropſie and Scurvy When theſe two Humours are mixed together and hard to be parted. It doth help ſower Belches, and cauſeth a good Appetite, the obſtruction of the Liver and Spleen, Agues and Feavers of all ſorts. It preſently helpeth Vomiting, and giveth preſent eaſe for the Griping pains of the Guts, and in a few times taking it maketh a Cure, as it may be witneſſed by Mr. <hi>Ward</hi> of Bi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hop's-head Court in <hi>Grayes-Inn-Lane,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Michill</hi> of Angel-alley in the ſame Lane, for himſelf and daughter, with Thouſands more which are bound to bleſs God for the ſpeedy Comfort they have found by this thing: the Wind-Collick, and Strangury, and pains in the Bladder. It doth preſently help bleeding by Urine or Stool, the Jaundies yellow and black; the Mother and Spleen, Running pains in the Joints. It doth pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve Women from miſcarrying: what I ſay of it, is of a real truth, and it is as ſafe to take as a bit of Bread, and doth not Purge, nor Vomit, nor diſtemper the Body any manner of way but giveth eaſe in moſt Diſtempers in about an hours time, with the bleſſing of God: and for the pain of the Collick, if it be of Wind, Sand, Gravel, or tough ſlimy humors, it doth give preſent eaſe as aforeſaid: It doth commonly bring away Stones as big as Peaſe, and abundance of Gravel from Men and Women: what I have ſpoken of this thing is true, for I have proved it for many years. It helpeth the Rickets in Children, and ſuch as are torubled with Pthiſick, Cough, or Conſumption, and pining away with loſs of their fleſh, if they be not too far ſpent, it will ſoon recover them, it is no matter what age they are; I have helpt hundreds ſince my coming to <hi>London,</hi> as you may read of ſome of their names in this Book, which were pined away to skin and bones, and done it in a ſhort time with ſmall charge.</p>
            <p>I cure all ſorts of Blindneſs, or any diſtemper in the Eyes (ſo far as curable) without pain, or putting any thing into them, and take away the cauſes thereof, ſo that they are not troubled any more therewith: therefore I adviſe you not to put any thing at all into your Eyes, for that never taketh away the cauſe, neither can it cure but cauſeth much pain, and many times putteth the Eyes out, or at leaſt maketh them paſt cure; then for you that ever intend to have cure, put not any thing at all into your eyes.</p>
            <p>I cure any ſort of Burſteneſs in Men, Women and Children, and keep a Truſs-maker on purpoſe to make Truſſes for them; otherwiſe they cannot be cured.</p>
            <p>I cure any ſort of Deafneſs provided it came not with blowes, the ſound of B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lls, the ſhooting off Guns, or that the Organ of the Ear be not fallen together, then you may have cure without pain.</p>
            <p>I cure the Scald or Leproſie-head, without pain or loſs of a hair of the head, as you may read among the cures you will find where I have done the like. I have preſent help for ſuch as cannot make water but with great pain, and take away all ſharpneſs of Urine though never ſo bad, and give preſent eaſe. I cure all ſorts of Wens without cutting, or any other ſort of Tumor let it be what it will. I cure Convulſions, Falling-ſickneſs, and Fits of the Mother, Dropſie and Tympany, Conſumption, and Cough, in ſuch as are almoſt at Deaths-door, the Jaundies yellow and black, the Evil of any ſort, the Cancer, Wolf, Fiſtula, the Ague and Feaver, all pains in the Head though it be Megrim, Vertigo, Lethargies, or Apoplexies, pains in the Shoulders, Armes, Stomack, Sides, Belly, and Bick, Knees, Legs, Ankles and Feet.</p>
            <p>I would not have any to be ſo fooliſh as to queſtion the truth thereof, ſeeing you have the names of ſo many witneſſes ſet down in this Book which I have already cured, their names and places where they live round about you, and you will find it as true as I ſay, and if there be any cure, you ſhall have it ſpeedily and for ſmall charge.</p>
            <p>I ſhould not need to have ſpoke ſo much, but that I find the people ſome of them very faithleſs, and I ſuppoſe that is, becauſe the Cheats have guld them of their money, therefore I adviſe you not to make uſe of every one alike, but diligently to enquire for him that is known to do great Cures, for by ſuch means you may have help, for he knows preſently what good can be done for you, and do you good if poſſible there be any help, but thoſe that have practiſed but a little while, they muſt practiſe on your bodies ſeven and ſeven years, before they can have the experience to do Cures. I have had ſeveral times in my travels ten or twenty pounds for a Cure, after the Women and other unskilful perſons have done with it, which if they had gone to an able Phyſician at the firſt might have had help for a Crown, or it may be leſs, but there are ſo many of theſe young Doctors in every corner, that no ſooner any perſon falls into any Diſtemper, but they are ready at hand, and will undertake the Cure preſently, there they podder with their ſorceries till they have either killed them, or made them paſt Cure, and if they cure one by chance, though they kill hundreds afterward, they will ſay their times were come, and in this manner Thouſands of the meaner ſort of people loſe their lives; the truth is, Millions of people are bound to curſe all that practiſe on peoples bodies without art, for Phyſick is a very dangerous thing for unskilful people to meddle with.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> will of their own <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:104839:6"/>
            <p>There are ſome Men and Women, becauſe their friend doth practiſe Phyſick, they will make uſe of none but him; It is true, my friend will do what he can for me, but when my life is gone my friend cannot help me to it again: therefore if I hear of any that hath more skill than my friend, I will make uſe of him, and yet love my friend well, but my life better.</p>
            <p>Many of the people before they are helpt, when they lie in great miſery, Oh! what they would give for eaſe, but when I have made them well, they ſay ſurely it was but a ſmall Diſtemper, becauſe he did it with ſo ſmall a matter, and for ſo little money.</p>
            <p>I helpt the wife of Mr. <hi>Midaleton,</hi> at the ſign of the <hi>Golden Patton,</hi> over againſt the <hi>Kings-beech</hi> in <hi>Southwark,</hi> of the Dropſie, who had loſt the greateſt part of her blood, ſo that ſhe had little or nothing left in the Veins but watery humours which, turned to a ſad Dropſie, with great weakneſs, and this came with a miſcarriage of two Children at one birth.</p>
            <p>I cured Mr. <hi>Iohn Cherſly,</hi> living at the Sign of the Swan and Key in <hi>Brick-lane</hi> in <hi>Old-ſtreet,</hi> who had been Deaf and troubled with great noiſe in his Head about forty years, he was quite Deaf, and threeſcore and ſeventeen years of age when I cured him; both he and his wife returned thanks both to God and me, and he heareth very well. Mr. <hi>William Shearman</hi> in <hi>Black-Fryers</hi> over againſt the <hi>Dark-entry,</hi> of the Stone and Gravel in the Kidneys and Bladder, and of the Sciatica pain in his Hip, and I helpt him in a fortnights time with Gods help two years ſince, and cannot hear that he was troubled any more therewith.</p>
            <p>I helpt Mr. <hi>Ralph Steel</hi> of <hi>Clarken-well,</hi> the next door to the ſign of the <hi>Flying-horſe,</hi> of a Conſumption and great weakneſs. Now if I ſhould adviſe you to have of my Balſome of Balſoms, and keep it in readineſs in the houſe, it may be you would ſay I ſpeak for my own ends to ſell my Balſome. I ſay no, I do not, for it is but one ſhilling the ounce, and it is ready if you ſhould have a Burn, a Scald, or Squat, a Bruiſe, a Straine, a Cut, or any other miſchance, which will come in Families, and you may look for them every day; and when any of theſe diſtempers comes, and having nothing to apply ſo ſoon as it is hurt, it runs on till it doth coſt a Crown or an Angel the cure, and ſometimes loſe the uſe of a member or a joint, after you have endured ſo much pain and miſery. This my Balſome taketh away the pain of a Burn or Scald, ſo ſoon as laid to the part grieved, and cureth without Scar, they which know the goodneſs of it keep it in the houſe by them; reaſon may tell you that if it were not ſo good as I ſay, it would not be for me to ſtand by it, and vindicate the truth of it, which I ſhall do whilſt I have breath.</p>
            <p>I helpt the wife of Mr. <hi>Olive</hi> at the ſign of the Cock going into the Market place in Newgate Market, of the Stone and Gravil, when ſhe was very bad indeed.</p>
            <p>The Cheats and their relations will ſay, he is a Mountibank, why will you go to him? But I ſay if I am a Mountibank, where is my Stage, why do they belie me?</p>
            <p>You may have more good of me for a Crown, or an Angel, than you can have at any other place for forty ſhillings.</p>
            <p>I cured the wife of Mr. <hi>Iſaiah Palmer</hi> the next door to the ſign of the <hi>Old Shears</hi> in <hi>Great Wood-ſtreet</hi> of a cancered Wen on her hand which was breeding about twelve years. The Daughter of Mr. <hi>Mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ith</hi> at the ſign of the <hi>Five Bells</hi> in <hi>Grey<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>-Inn-lane,</hi> of the Feaver with gripes of the Guts. The Daughter of Mr. <hi>Bignall</hi> at the ſign of the <hi>White-horſe</hi> ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r <hi>York-houſe</hi> in the <hi>Strand,</hi> of the Evil in her Neck. Mr. <hi>Seal</hi> at the <hi>Soap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>box</hi> in <hi>Holborn,</hi> of the Feaver and gripes of the Guts. Mr. <hi>John Hayes</hi>'s ſon of <hi>Crown-Court,</hi> in <hi>Baldwins-Gardens,</hi> of a lame Arm, who had no uſe of it, and I made him as well as ever he was in his life.</p>
            <p>I cured the Child of Mr. <hi>John Sarrit,</hi> living at the upper end of <hi>Sea-alley</hi> in <hi>Kings-ſtreet</hi> in <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> being pined away with a Confumption to skin and bones, being above two years of age, and could not bear any ſtrength to ſtand, and people thought it was unpoſſible for that Child to be recovered; however with Gods bleſſing he is grown as brave a lively Boy as any about <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I helpt the Child of Mr. <hi>John Scott</hi> of Roſe-alley in Golden-lane of the Convulſions and the Evil in his eyes; the daughter of Mr. <hi>Standbridge</hi> in Catherine-wheele-yard, over againſt the Sheep Pens in Smithfield of the Feaver, with Gripes in the Guts; Mrs. <hi>Margaret Guiny</hi> of Church-yard-Alley in Chick-lane, of great pain <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>her ſtomach and back, and Vomiting; Mr. <hi>Barnes</hi> of Hornſie four miles from London of the Ague, the ſon of Mr. <hi>Keytte</hi> of Catherine-wheele-yard in Smithfield of the Conſuming feaver which is the worſt of Conſumptions.</p>
            <p>Mrs. <hi>Mary Rogers,</hi> of <hi>Harp-ally</hi> in <hi>Smithfield,</hi> of the Feaver and Gripes of the Guts, when ſhe lay ſo weak that none thought ſhe would have lived, I cured her at the <hi>Golden-Cock</hi> in <hi>Shooe-lane,</hi> where I cured <hi>Mary Cox</hi> alſo of the ſame Diſtemper; the Chid of <hi>Theophilus Farmer,</hi> of <hi>Harts-born-lane,</hi> near the Sign of the <hi>Plow,</hi> in the <hi>Strand,</hi> near <hi>Northamberland-houſe,</hi> of the Rickets, who was two years old and a half, and could not bear any ſtrength to ſtand, and pined away to skin and bones, and I made him able, with God's help, to goe about the houſe by hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:104839:6"/>
            <p>I would adviſe all thoſe that have unfortunately taken <hi>Mercury,</hi> and that it hath not all workt it ſelf out of the Body, which you may know by little pricking Pains in the Head and Noſe and other parts of the Body, with great Weakneſs, I have a Pill which will fetch it out though it hath lain never ſo long in the Body, and not hinder any buſineſs; I have proved it by hundreds within theſe two years, and it never failed me.</p>
            <p>I cured Mr. <hi>Fidiman</hi> at the ſign of the <hi>White Lyon</hi> at the lower end of <hi>Hatton Garden</hi> in <hi>Holborn,</hi> of the Cough, about two years ago, who hath not been troubled <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ce.</p>
            <p>Mrs. <hi>Mialeton</hi> at the <hi>Golden Patton,</hi> over againſt the <hi>Kings Be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch</hi> in <hi>Southwark,</hi> of a moſt violent Head-ach, who could not get help by any other.</p>
            <p>I ſhall here ſet down the Cure of one Mrs. <hi>Terry,</hi> being deſired ſo to doe both by her husband and her I if;<note place="margin">☜</note>her Diſeaſe was a ſtoppage fallen into her Kidneys which cauſed an extraordinary racking and torturing P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>in in her Back alſo a great paine and weakneſs in her Hips an Limbs downwards: this Diſtemper ſeaſed her immediately after my going into the Country, whereupon ſhe couſulted the beſt means ſhe could for her Cure, but found none to be effectual; at my returne to <hi>London</hi> ſhe ſent her water to me, by which, and other circumſtances I found her to be in a very deſperate Condition, and that in all likelihood, ſhe could not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ive above a day or two, whereupon I adminiſtred ſome thing to her, and in once taking ſhe found a great benefit by it, which gave me Incouragement to proceed in the Cure which it pleaſed God in a very ſhort time to make effectual and parfect; ſhe liv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th at the bunch of Grapes near the <hi>Kings-bench</hi> in <hi>Southwark</hi> where both ſhe and her family are able to atteſt the truth hereof.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Cordial Pill</hi> being taken often when Woman is with Child prevents miſcarying.</p>
            <p>Since my going it to the Countrey, the Cheats have been at work again, ſaying they have a <hi>Cordial Water</hi> or <hi>Spirit</hi> to cure all Diſeaſes, and uſe all the chief words of my Book in their Papers for the ſelling of them, word by word as it is ſet down of my <hi>Cordial Pill,</hi> and by that means they have deceived many; Therefore I deſire you to beware of them, for I have had great Complaints by many people, how they have been Cheated of their money, becauſe they thought thoſe <hi>Waters</hi> or <hi>Spi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>its</hi> had been ſet forth by my Order, they finding the ſame words of my Book in their Papers. I deſire you will but make farther enquiry of thoſe who ſell theſe <hi>Waters</hi> or <hi>Spirits,</hi> and I ſuppoſe you will find them to be but young Beginners, and know little or nothing in the Art of Phyſick; and therefore you will be at a great loſs if you let them try Practice on your Bodies; for you may lay any thing that is Purging in ſteep all night, in any Strong-waters or Spirits, and drink off the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor, and it will Purge more or leſs as you will. But woe to them that drink it, becauſe theſe Waters or Spirits will be always ſending the Phyſical part into the habit of the body, ſo that at other times when you are not well, and muſt be forced to take Phyſick, take notice that whatſoever you take will work upon Nature more then upon the Diſtemper, and the ſign will be your fleſh will fall away when you take any thing to Purge. Any able Doctor will tell you, that Strong-waters or Spirits drank wherein Purging things have been infuſed, cannot cure a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtemper, but will corrupt the whole maſs of blood, and ſhorten life, though it may be pleaſant in time of taking by ſuch as love ſtrong Liquors; therefore have a care you are not cheated of your money, but your lives alſo, for I utterly diſown that ever I have any hand in ſelling, or ordering any ſuch Spirits or Waters to be ſold, neither ſhall there be any ſuch Waters or Spirits ſold by my order or conſent. That Strong-waters or Spirits which is diſtilled and made of mens blood, whoſoever drinketh thereof will be troubled with the ſame diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per the man or woman was, which they had the blood from; and if that man hath any diſtemper afterwards, the man or woman which drank of thoſe Waters or Spirits will have the ſame diſtemper, as I have it by Tradition.</p>
            <p>Alſo the Strong-waters or Spirits made of men and womens piſs, which have been too frequently ſold of late, are very unwholſome.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The <hi>Engliſh Phyſicians</hi> Friendly PILL.</head>
               <p>THis is the <hi>PILL</hi> of my long ſtudy, which cureth the Scurvey when it is grown to that height, that it makes many people fear they have got a worſe diſeaſe, and I think that can hardly be; for it will cauſe great pains in the head, and ſometimes pricking pains in the noſe, and much dulneſs and heavineſs of body; ſome will have pains in the ſhoulders or arms, between the elbow and the ſhoulder, in others pains in the ſhin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bones, and in ſome pains in the joynts, in others pains all over, with foulneſs of the ſtomach, tongue and teeth, and loſs of appetite; it will cauſe pains in the back and bladder, like the reliques of an old Gonorrhea, which was not well cured, or like thoſe which have taken <hi>Mercury</hi> ill prepared, that cannot work it ſelf out of the body; their water will alter according to what they eat and drink, but moſt commonly in men it will be high <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:104839:7"/>they ſeldom make a good water, and as ſeldom enjoy any perfect health: ſometimes they think they have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> diſeaſe, and ſometimes another; they are often ſeeking for help, but get but little: the Urine of women that have this diſeaſe, in ſome it will be of a ſad colour, but in moſt it will be pale or greeniſh, with a whitiſh ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling at the bottom when it hath ſtood a while; ſome will have little knobs in the skin, ſome break out with little pimples about the body, and knobs in the head, others bad ſleep, with confuſed dreams, and when they have had it ſome years they grow melancholly, and enjoy nothing: ſome it bringeth into a Dropſie and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption; this <hi>Pill</hi> cureth this diſtemper, and the Gonorrhea, and all manner of Venereal diſeaſes, from the greateſt to the ſmalleſt, although they have had it twenty years; and if the Scurvey, or either of the diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers have been but a little while, once taking cureth; but if either of theſe diſtempers be old and ſtubborn, it will require more, and if you find the firſt taking doth not the cure, take one Doſe every third night going to bed till you have taken four or five times, it will not hinder your reſt, but make it better, and in the morning it will bring away more poiſon and corruption at one ſtool, then any other will do at twenty times taking; it doth give almoſt a Chamber-pot full the firſt ſtool, and two or three ſmall ſtools of corruption afterwards, and not gripe at all, nor make you ſick, nor diſorder you any manner of way, any more then what I have told you; and you may go where you pleaſe, and do what you pleaſe, as if you took nothing at all, and it will not fail you. I have known it cure Ulcers in the throat and bladder. Once taking helps thoſe who have any way foul'd the ſtomach with drinking. Theſe <hi>Pills</hi> are of ſuch a body, that they cannot loſe their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> in an hundred years; they are admirable for ſuch as go to Sea, or that Trade into any other Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, for they lie in a little room, and nothing can hurt them; and moſt commonly they cure any diſtemper at the firſt taking, if it be taken at the firſt beginning: and reaſon may tell you the ſame, if it bringeth away ſo much corruption out of the body at once taking. I never gave it to Children, for they are not troubled with any ſuch diſtemper, unleſs it comes hereditary. I always ſold the Doſe of Pills for five ſhillings, and now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Poor ſhall have the benefit as well as the Rich, I will ſell them for one ſhilling the Doſe, which is twen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Pills in number, which you may put into a Spoon with a little Ale or Beer, and ſwallow them all at once <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the pulp of an Apple, or any way you can beſt take them: they are eaſie enough to take, being in big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and may be taken at any time of the year, and they will do as I have ſaid with Gods bleſſing. They are ſealed up in wooden Boxes with my own Seal, twenty in a Box for one ſhilling, and forty in a Box two ſhillings, and ſixty in a Box three ſhillings, and eighty in a Box four ſhillings, and one hundred in a Box five ſhillings, and they are for five times taking, that is twenty every third or fourth night going to Bed: I have not known them fail Cure of any Ach in the bones being curable. I have left them to be ſold by my Truſty Friends Mr. <hi>Tailor</hi> next door to the Golden Still and D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>agon over againſt <hi>Charter-houſe-lane</hi> end, at <hi>Cow-Croſs;</hi> Mr. <hi>Smith</hi> at the Golden Patten over againſt the <hi>Kings-Bench</hi> in <hi>Southwark;</hi> Mr. <hi>Coe</hi> on the Bank-ſide near the Bear-garden, <hi>Southwark;</hi> Mrs. <hi>Landſdel</hi> in <hi>Swithens-alley</hi> near the <hi>Royal Exchange,</hi> Coffee-houſe; Mr. <hi>Naper</hi> in <hi>Bell-alley</hi> in <hi>Goſwell ſtreet;</hi> Mr. <hi>Mortlock</hi> at the White Hart in <hi>Weſtminſter-hall,</hi> Bookſeller, and at the Phaenix in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard; Mr. <hi>Young</hi> of <hi>Park-ſtreet</hi> near St. <hi>Albans;</hi> Mr. <hi>Kirwood</hi> of <hi>Corn-ſtreet</hi> in <hi>Briſtol;</hi> and at my houſe in <hi>Hatten-Garden,</hi> and at my houſe at <hi>Marſhfield</hi> in <hi>Glouceſter-ſhire,</hi> and at no other place in the World. The Cheats can hardly counterfeit this <hi>Pill,</hi> but I believe they will be endeavouring in a ſhort time.</p>
               <p>I deſire you farther to take notice, that my <hi>Cordial Pill</hi> and <hi>Balſom of Balſoms</hi> is ſold by my order, by Mr. <hi>Naper</hi> of <hi>Bell-alley</hi> in <hi>Goſwell-ſtreet,</hi> Mr. <hi>Tailor</hi> over againſt <hi>Charter-houſe-lane</hi> end, next to the Golden Still and Dragon, Mr. <hi>Richard Young</hi> of <hi>Park-ſtreet</hi> near St. <hi>Albans,</hi> Mr. <hi>Kirwood</hi> Apothecary in <hi>Corn-ſtreet</hi> in <hi>Briſtol,</hi> and at my houſe in <hi>Hatten-Garden,</hi> and my houſe at <hi>Marſhfield,</hi> and no other place in the World.</p>
               <p>YOu are earneſtly deſired to communicate this Book to your Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours and Friends, which may be a means of much good to them and many others.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>You may ſpeak with me from</hi> 9 <hi>of the Clock in the Morning, till</hi> 5 <hi>in the Afternoon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I have an <hi>Electuary</hi> that infallibly Cureth all manner of pains in the Back, cauſeth good quiet ſleep, and a good Appetite, and ſtrengtheneth the whole body very much, and cauſeth a good <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:104839:7"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
